Finding aid to Alumnae Oral History Project collection CA.MS.00301
Smith College Archives
- Alumnae Oral History Project interviews (2013), Accession 2012-A-0026
  - Camille O'Bryant (Class of 1983) interviewed by Anne Ames, 2013 May 18; 1 oral histories (transcript and video)
    In this oral history, Camille O'Bryant speaks about the critical role that athletics played in her Smith career and about discovering later the historic role Smith played in women's sports. She reflects on the people who helped her overcome the challenges Smith presented her with, including Jill Kerr Conway, and how that experience instilled in her the importance of giving back.
    - Video interview with Camille O'Bryant
    - Transcript of interview with Camille O'Bryant (Box 10)
  - Eileen M. Ouellette (Class of 1958) interviewed by Ellice Amanna, 2013 May 24; 1 oral histories (transcript and video)
    This interview is available for research without restriction. No online video.
    In this oral history, Dr. Eileen Ouellette speaks from the perspective of her 55th reunion week. She recalls the preparation she received at Smith which allowed her to go on to Harvard Medical School and a career that has combined medicine and social justice activism, including national advocacy on behalf of victims of Hurricane Katrina, particularly, children.
    - Video interview with Eileen M. Ouellette
    - Transcript of interview with Eileen Ouellette (Box 10)
  - Barbara Pilvin (Class of 1973) interviewed by Carolyn Rees, 2013 May 25; 1 oral histories (transcript and video)
    In this oral history, Barbara Pilvin relates memories of Smith professors who made important and lasting impressions on her. She recalls a life-changing year abroad and talks about the importance of reunion and why she has only missed one since her graduation.
    - Video interview with Barbara Pilvin
    - Video interview with Barbara Pilvin (Box 10)
  - Catherine Pyun (Class of 1988) interviewed by Carolyn Rees, 2013 May 18; 1 oral histories (transcript and video)
    This interview is available for research only to members of the Smith Community. No online access.
    In this oral history Catherine Pyun speaks during her 25th reunion weekend. She discusses the role that her first visit to campus played her decision to apply to Smith and of making lifelong friends, including through her participation in sports. She also discusses the importance of having an engineering and science program for women at Smith.
    - Video interview with Catherine Pyun
    - Transcript of interview with Catherine Pyun (Box 10)
  - Eva Rabin (Class of 2008) interviewed by Anne Ames, 2013 May 17; 1 oral histories (transcript and video)
    In this oral history Eva Rabin discusses the pull that attending Smith reunions has for her and her friends. She recalls her decision to go to Smith after attending an alumnae reception in California and her continuing admiration for Smith graduates. Rabin recalls her junior year abroad in Scotland and the ways in which that experience changed her future.
    - Video interview with Eva Rabin
    - Transcript of interview with Eva Rabin (Box 10)
  - Emma Roderick and Justine Sheffler (Class of 2008) interviewed by Rachel Klinger, 2013 May 17; 1 oral histories (transcript and video)
    In this oral history, Emma Roderick and Justine Sheffler discuss changes in identity politics at Smith since their graduation. They recall social justice movements on campus and the learning that went on outside the classroom, through that activism. They share memories from their time at Smith, including of a favorite J-term origami class.
    - Video interview with Emma Roderick and Justine Sheffler
    - Transcript of interview with Emma Roderick and Justine Sheffler (Box 10)
  - Betsy Robins Rosenthal (Class of 1963) interviewed by Anne Ames, 2013 May 25; 1 oral histories (transcript and video)
    In this oral history Betsy Robins Rosenthal recalls her first days at Smith, the divisions she encountered among students along lines of race, religion and class, and the way she's observed diversity increasing on campus over the years. Asked about a "typical Smithie," she reflects on how different Smith students are from one another, but that they are also universally serious students who continually impress her.
    - Video interview with Betsy Robins Rosenthal
    - Transcript of interview with Betsy Robins Rosenthal (Box 10)
  - Susan Friebert Rossen (Class of 1963) interviewed by Ellice Amanna, 2013 May 25; 1 oral histories (transcript and video)
    In this oral history, Susan Friebert Rossen credits her Smith education, particularly her art history professors and her junior year in Paris, with giving her the foundation for a successful professional career. She talks about the experience of helping to prepare her class reunion book and all she learned while researching in the College Archives during that process.
    - Video interview with Susan Friebert Rossen
    - Transcript of interview with Susan Friebert Rossen (Box 10)
  - Alexandra Ross-Reid (Class of 2008) interviewed by Rachel Klinger, 2013 May 18; 1 oral histories (transcript and video)
    In this oral history, Alexandra Ross-Reid talks about the unique nature and the importance of Smith's house communities. She discusses her perspective as a woman of color and how navigating racial differences and looking at issues from a variety of perspectives during her Smith years prepared her for the world after graduation.
    - Video interview with Alexandra Ross-Reid
    - Transcript of interview with Alexandra Ross-Reid (Box 10)
  - Maria Christina Sclafani (Class of 2008) interviewed by Carolyn Rees, 2013 May 17; 1 oral histories (transcript and video)
    In this oral history, Maria Sclafani discusses the central role her house played in her Smith experience. She speaks of professors who played an important role in her Smith education, and recalls a charged political environment that was the backdrop to her college years. She also reflects on how being at Smith gave her an understanding of gender bias and the way that operates in the world, which has informed her post-graduate life.
    - Video interview with Maria Christina Sclafani
    - Transcript of interview with Maria Christina Sclafani (Box 10)
  - Miranda Simpson-Sawyer (Class of 2008) interviewed by Anne Ames, 2013 May 18; 1 oral histories (transcript and video)
    In this oral history, Miranda Simpson-Sawyer recalls the culture shock she experienced on arriving at Smith as a first-year, her favorite Smith traditions, like Convocation, and some of the professors who served as important mentors, and how that influenced her choice of a major.
    - Video interview with Miranda Simpson-Sawyer
    - Transcript of interview with Miranda Simpson-Sawyer (Box 10)
  - Mary Oakes Smith (Class of 1963) interviewed by Carolyn Rees, 2013 May 24; 1 oral histories (transcript and video)
    In this oral history, Mary Oakes Smith speaks of the ways in which her Smith experience shaped her future activism and her career in international development. She talks about the importance of Smith's Engineering School, and the emphasis on a global education and community service, and recalls professors and classes that presented her with unique opportunities.
    - Video interview with Mary Oakes Smith
    - Transcript of interview with Mary Oakes Smith (Box 10)
  - Lysbeth (Libby) Stone (Class of 1953) interviewed by Ellice Amanna, 2013 May 25; 1 oral histories (transcript and video)
    In this oral history, Lysbeth (Libby) Stone, who has only missed one reunion since graduating Smith in 1953, tells stories from her Smith years, recalling that Sylvia Plath was in her Chaucer class and how evident it was that she was a unique talent.
    - Video interview with Lysbeth (Libby) Stone
    - Transcript of interview with Lysbeth (Libby) Stone (Box 10)
  - Anne Kingsley Thorpe (Class of 1943) interviewed by Carolyn Rees, 2013 May 25; 1 oral histories (transcript and video)
    In this oral history Anne Kingsley Thorpe looks back on her experience of being on campus during World War II, including rushing from classes to listen to reports of critical battles. She remembers Smith traditions which inspired her during her years on campus and the professors who shaped her college career.
    - Video interview with Anne Kingsley Thorpe
    - Transcript of interview with Anne Kingsley Thorpe (Box 10)
  - Martha Gregory Tolles (Class of 1943) interviewed by Carolyn Rees, 2013 May 24; 1 oral histories (transcript and video)
    In this oral history Martha Gregory Tolles recalls her experience being at Smith at the beginning of World War II. She recounts being called into her house mother's sitting room and listening to the news of the attack on Pearl Harbor, as well as work she did for the WAVES. She also tells of meeting her future husband on Mountain Day and recalls working on the college newspaper when Betty Friedan was editor.
    - Video interview with Martha Gregory Tolles
    - Transcript of interview with Martha Gregory Tolles (Box 10)
  - Berneta Walraven (Class of 1983) interviewed by Ellice Amanna, 2013 May 25; 1 oral histories (transcript and video)
    In this oral history, Berneta Walraven speaks about her the graduation commitment she made to attend Smith reunions and discusses the central role the crew team played in her Smith career. She speaks about her personal identity and political journey, and how that influenced her career as an activist. She discusses the central role the crew team played in her Smith career.
    - Video interview with Berneta Walraven
    - Transcript of interview with Berneta Walraven (Box 10)
  - Barbara Ehrlich White (Class of 1958) interviewed by Carolyn Rees, 2013 May 24; 1 oral histories (transcript and video)
    In this oral history, Barbara Ehrlich White discusses her view of reunions as markers in our life journey. She looks back on her Smith experience and reflects on the importance of her junior year in Paris in preparing her for her career as an art history professor and author. She credits her Smith training in art history as foundational for her later success.
    - Video interview with Barbara Ehrlich White
    - Transcript of interview with Barbara Ehrlich White (Box 10)
- Records and release forms, 2010-2013 (Box 11)
  RESTRICTED
- Alumnae Oral History Project interviews (2014), Accession 2012-A-0026
  - Tammy Baldwin (Class of 1984) interviewed by Grace Ramsay, 2014 May 16; 1 oral histories (transcript and video)
    In this interview, Tammy Baldwin reflects on her time at Smith, including her favorite traditions and house community. She recalls coming out and the general campus attitude towards lesbians at the time. She also mentions the political controversies at Smith and beyond during her time here. Baldwin then talks about her journey to becoming the first openly lesbian senator and the shift from working with local Wisconsin politics to serving in the legislature. She talks about the experience of running for office as a woman and the difficulties associated with it. She speaks to her work on LGBT policy and offers advice to student activists and graduating Smithies. The interview ends with Baldwin offering ways to stay hopeful in the harsh political climate of the digital media age.
    - Video interview with Tammy Baldwin
    - Transcript of interview with Tammy Baldwin (Box 12)
  - Joan Bouchard (Class of 1964) interviewed by Grace Ramsay, 2014 May 16; 1 oral histories (transcript and video)
    Joan Bouchard begins by recalling her time living in Dawes House and the exploits in which she participated. She brings up the importance of listening to contrasting opinions in the context of both George Wallace and Christine Lagarde. She also discusses the importance of believing that one can change the world and having an activist attitude. She tells about her involvement in sports at Smith and her positive experience with the posture requirements and her basic motor skills class. Next, she brings up her enjoyment of work study jobs that others might have disliked. The interview concludes with Bouchard remembering how Smith professors helped her understand her own value and intelligence, which has helped her get through many difficult times in her life.
    - Video interview with Joan Bouchard
    - Transcript of interview with Joan Bouchard (Box 12)
  - Karen Bouchard (Class of 1984) interviewed by Julia Greider, 2014 May 17; 1 oral histories (transcript and video)
    In this interview, Karen Bouchard recalls the good times had with her friends in Wilder House and her love of the house system. She talks about being an art history major and the professors in that department who had a strong influence on her. She goes on to discuss the political issues of her time on campus, including the election of Reagan. She brings up the tensions over the presence of lesbians at Smith, as well as the controversy over and consequences of inviting Jeane Kirkpatrick to speak at Commencement. Finally, she discusses the challenges of being a first-generation college student at Smith and ends by recalling the campus reaction to John Lennon's assassination.
    - Video interview with Karen Bouchard
    - Transcript of interview with Karen Bouchard (Box 12)
  - Linda Charles (Class of 1974) interviewed by Nina Goldman, 2014 May 17; 1 oral histories (transcript and video)
    In this interview, Linda Charles discusses a wide range of her experiences during and after Smith. She discusses attending Smith during a socially tumultuous time especially around racial diversity, and the student activism that occurred on campus in response. Charles speaks highly of friend, mentor, and student activist Phoebe Haddon, and recalls having meaningful discussions with her professors about being a student of color. Charles describes her professional life after Smith and attributes her success to some of the skills she learned in college. Towards the end of the interview, Charles discusses her position as a trustee and her current perspective on the commencement speaker controversy of 2014. Charles closes with thoughts on the future of Smith and advice to current students. Screen reader support enabled. In this interview, Linda Charles discusses a wide range of her experiences during and after Smith. She discusses attending Smith during a socially tumultuous time especially around racial diversity, and the student activism that occurred on campus in response. Charles speaks highly of friend, mentor, and student activist Phoebe Haddon, and recalls having meaningful discussions with her professors about being a student of color. Charles describes her professional life after Smith and attributes her success to some of the skills she learned in college. Towards the end of the interview, Charles discusses her position as a trustee and her current perspective on the commencement speaker controversy of 2014. Charles closes with thoughts on the future of Smith and advice to current students.
    - Video interview with Linda Charles
    - Transcript of interview with Linda Charles (Box 12)
  - Sally Katzen Dyk (Class of 1964) interviewed by Julia Greider, 2014 May 17; 1 oral histories (transcript and video)
    Sally Katzen Dyk begins her interview with a story about being one of the "dirty dozen," a group that the dean admitted to Smith in spite of their low SAT scores, and who went on to be leaders on campus. She discusses her interest in the Civil Rights Movement, which was sparked by seeing the "I Have a Dream" speech and manifested itself in her role in organizing the Southern Student Exchange at Smith. She talks about her experiences with racism when she spent a week at an all-black college in the South. She recalls the assassination of JFK on her birthday as well as her role on campus during 9/11, when she had just returned to Smith as a professor. She considers the differences between the college in the 1960s and in the 2000s. Additionally, she discusses her work in three presidential administrations and the confidence that Smith gave her for her career.
    Dyk, Sally Katzen, Class of 1964
    - Video interview of Sally Katzen Dyk
    - Transcript of interview with Sally Katzen Dyk (Box 12)
  - Erin Fray (Class of 1984) interviewed by Grace Ramsay, 2014 May 17; 1 oral histories (transcript and video)
    In this interview, Erin Fray recalls her experience living in Dawes House for her sophomore and senior years (she spent her junior year abroad). Mostly reflecting on the specific house activities and cultural community Dawes had to offer, Erin also speaks to the friendships she made at Smith. She concludes by describing Smith as an empowering place that celebrates diversity.
    - Video interview with Erin Fray
    - Transcript of interview with Erin Fray (Box 12)
  - Joan Gass (Class of 1964) interviewed by Nina Goldman, 2014 May 16; 1 oral histories (transcript and video)
    In this interview, Joan Gass recalls her journey to Smith and her two years here. Feeling like an outsider compared to the "typical" Smithie, she has a different perspective on social life and traditions on campus. She reflects on the political climate at Smith and her own political canvassing she did here. Joan talks about transferring to Brown her sophomore year after marrying her husband, because Smith only allowed single students at the time. She speaks to the sexism she experienced at Smith and at Brown as a married student. Joan ends the interview by remembering how women in her class either married or aimed for more degrees after Smith, because a Smith education did not guarantee a career.
    - Video interview with Joan Gass
    - Transcript of interview with Joan Gass (Box 12)
  - Julia Hayden (Class of 1994) interviewed by Nina Goldman, 2014 May 16; 1 oral histories (transcript and video)
    In this interview, Hayden talks about her experience as part of a class year that was marked by racial tension. She discusses her experience of Lamont House community, racial tensions from the perspective of a white Southerner, and working long hours as the Sophian editor. Hayden ends the interview with advice and reflections on racial issues at Smith.
    - Video interview with Julia Hayden
    - Transcript of interview with Julia Hayden (Box 12)
  - Shaun Hunter (Class of 1984) interviewed by Grace Ramsay, 2014 May 17; 1 oral histories (transcript and video)
    In this interview, Shaun Hunter talks about being an international student from Canada at Smith and how it shaped her experiences here. She describes her difficulty adjusting to Jordan House in the distinctly American setting of Smith College, and consistently feeling like an outsider in this regard. She discusses feminism in the context of being an English major and ponders what a "typical Smithie" may be. Hunter discusses Smith as a complex intersection of issues and experiences that she continues to reflect on. The interview closes with Hunter's advice for future Smithies.
    - Video interview with Shaun Hunter
    - Transcript of interview with Shaun Hunter (Box 12)
  - Ellen Hurwitz (Class of 1964) interviewed by Julia Greider, 2014 May 16; 1 oral histories (transcript and video)
    Ellen Hurwitz places a lot of emphasis on her academic experiences in this interview. She begins by telling a story about being reprimanded for knitting in class. She goes on to discuss the dating culture and how people reacted to her Judaism. She also talks about what it was like to study Russian in the Cold War era, as well as what it meant to be a woman in the 1960s. She emphasizes the importance of being open to hearing various points of view so that they can be dealt with in the wider world, and she expresses thankfulness that Smith exposed her to so many different viewpoints and subjects. She concludes by discussing what it feels like to come back for the first reunion she has attended.
    - Video interview with Ellen Hurwitz
    - Transcript of interview with Ellen Hurwitz (Box 12)
  - Nicole James (Class of 1994) interviewed by Grace Ramsay, 2014 May 17; 1 oral histories (transcript and video)
    This interview is available for research to the Smith community only.
    In this oral history, Nicole James talks about finding a strong house community in Tyler House and her favorite traditions there. She also talks about the highly politicized campus and "politically correct" culture, which was polarizing, especially for students of color. Nicole speaks to the impact that attending reunions has had on her. The interview ends with Nicole saying this oral history project is essential for gaining the perspective of women of color at Smith.
    - Video interview with Nicole James
    - Transcript of interview with Nicole James (Box 12)
  - Terry Kitay (Class of 1984) interviewed by Julia Greider, 2014 May 17; 1 oral histories (transcript and video)
    In this interview, Terry Kitay discusses her interest in history and African American studies, as well as her passion for civil rights. She talks about her perception of lesbians on campus in the 1980s. She also tells about her career as a housing discrimination lawyer since graduation. Finally, she remembers both the good times with her friends in 150 Elm and the challenges with which Smith presented her.
    - Video interview with Terry Kitay
    - Transcript of interview with Terry Kitay (Box 12)
  - Sylvia Lewis (Class of 1974) interviewed by Nina Goldman, 2014 May 17; 1 oral histories (transcript and video)
    In this interview, Sylvia Lewis discusses her experiences as a member of the class of '74, which had the largest amount of admitted African American students in Smith's history. Lewis discusses her first experience at Smith, a party thrown by Smith's Black Students Alliance to encourage newly admitted Black students to come to Smith. During her time at Smith, Lewis was part of a very active student group who were instrumental in the formation of the African American studies program. Lewis mentions the other contributions of her class, including a Black theater group, the Mwangi Cultural Center, and the Black Alumnae Association.
    - Video interview with Sylvia Lewis
    - Transcript of interview with Sylvia Lewis (Box 12)
  - Angela Margolis (Class of 1964) interviewed by Grace Ramsay, 2014 May 17; 1 oral histories (transcript and video)
    Angela Margolis reflects upon her college experience as the first Smithie from North Dakota. In this interview, she talks about negotiating her class and national identity as she moved back and forth between North Dakota and Massachusetts. She speaks to the dating culture and the rigid rules set by house mothers. She also recalls specific anecdotes about her and her friends breaking those rules. Margolis then remembers specific events during her Smith career, such as hearing Eudora Welty and Robert Frost speak. She ends the interview by talking about finding her passion for theater after graduating, as well as her path towards becoming a wife, a mother, and a spiritual person.
    - Video interview with Angela Margolis
    - Transcript of interview with Angela Margolis (Box 12)
  - Molly McNulty (Class of 1984) interviewed by Nina Goldman, 2014 May 17; 1 oral histories (transcript and video)